<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[By the King] [a proclamation for buildings]</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22048</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8420</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123981</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33150814</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33150814</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28766</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22048)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28766)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1875:46)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[By the King] [a proclamation for buildings]</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the Deputies of Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped and creased, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Title and other title information from STC (2nd ed.); added title from first 2 lines of text.</note>
                  <note>"Giuen at our Mannour of Tuddington the 25. day of Iuly in the sixt yeere of our Raigne of Great Britaine, France and Ireland."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Building permits --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:28766:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He continuall new Buildings, and addition and increaſe of Buildings in</hi> and neere about the City of <hi>London</hi> is growen to that exceſſe, and doeth draw together ſuch an ouerflow of people, ſpecially of the meaner ſort, as can hardly be either ſed and ſuſteined, or preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in health or gouerned, which doth not onely threaten, but hath already bred &amp; brought forth at diuers times dearth of Victuals, infection of Plague, and minifold diſorders, which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in his Royall wiſedome before this time foreſeeing, hath ſince his happy comming to the Crowne, by two ſeueral Proclamations, The one in the ſecond yeere of his highneſſe Raigne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning building with Bricke, the other in the fift yere of his Raigne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning building vpon New foundations, (wherein neuertheleſſe the former ordinance touching Bricke buildings is continued) ſought to giue remedy and prouiſion for the ſame; But ſuch hath bene &amp; is the couetous deſire of gaine &amp; priuate benefit ariſing of ſuch Buildings, ioyned with a neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Iuſtices &amp; Officers in executing his Maieſties ſaid Proclamations, as many perſons haue preſumed &amp; aduentured to offend againſt them, both to the continuance and increaſe of the former euils and inconueniences, and to the maniſeſt ill example of contempt and diſobedience in a caſe ſo notorious, and in the view of the whole kingdome: His Maieſtie neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe not forgetting (though vpon ſo iuſt cauſe of indignation) his accuſtomed clemencie, hath thought good to make a difference between the offenders and their caſes, and for ſuch as haue offended in not building with Bricke, in as much as the offenders were in great multitude, and might haue ſome colour of neceſſity, or pretended impoſſibility, though vniuſtly, as themſelues muſt needs confeſſe, if they looke abroad, &amp; ſee what is done in other well polliced Cities of <hi>Europe,</hi> His high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe gaue order that after ſome exemplar cenſure of a few Offenders by ſentence in the <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> the reſidue ſhould be admitted to compoſition, according to his Maieſties Commiſſion of grace for that purpoſe granted, wherein his Maieſties expreſſe pleaſure was, That the Fines ſhould be ſo milde and moderate as might make the Offenders themſelues ſenſible of his Maieſties Ienitie &amp; gracious diſpoſition, and might make all others perceiue, That it was not his Maieſties profit that was ſought, but onely the repreſſing of the inconuenience, and the preſeruing of the authority of his Maieſties Royall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements for the publique good, from contempt. But for the ſecond for of offenders, which haue erected new founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions where no Buildings were before, which had no maner of circumſtance to extenuate their offence, but many to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate the ſame, being againſt a Proclamation ſo lately publiſhed, and ſo ſtraitly penned, &amp; immediatly after a ſeucre ſentence in the <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> his Maieſtie hath directed that all ſuch Offenders, (the number of which cannot be many being within the compaſſe of one yere) ſhalbe proceeded within in the <hi>Star-chamber.</hi> But as his Maieſtie doth not thinke fit to admit at all to grace that kind of Offenders, ſo his Highneſſe doth publiſh and declare, That for the other point of Bricke building, no man do hereafter expect any the like fauour of Compoſition, as his Maieſtie was pleaſed onely at this time for the auoyding of rigor and extremitie to grant &amp; extend: But his Maieſties wil and pleaſure is, That his ſaid ordinance be hereafter ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerued, and mainteined, and the offenders againſt the ſame with all ſeueritie puniſhed. And to the end to remoue &amp; take away all colour of pretended neceſſity in that point, His Maieſtie is graciouſly pleaſed that his former Proclamations be explained &amp; qualified in maner and forme following, That is to ſay, That if any perſon that ſhall hereafter erect any buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon ad old foundation within the precincts limitted in the Proclamation publiſhed in the fift yeere of his Highneſſe raigne, ſhal make it appeare, That either the quantitie of the ground whereupon the old Foundation ſtandeth, is of too ſmal a proportion to receiue a Bricke building, or that the houſe is ſituate in ſo obſcure or meane a Lane of Alley, as is not fit for ſuch a Building, or that the trade of ſuch perſon as intendeth ſuch building, is the trade of a retayling ſhopkeeper, &amp; of ſuch a nature as his ſhop and building cannot with any conuenience be built with Bricke, and thereupon ſhall obtaine certificate vnder the hands of the Lord Maior, the Recorder, and the Alderman of the Ward, if the building be within the City or the Liberties thereof, and vnder the hands of two Iuſtices of the Peace, whereof one to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> if it be out of the City and Liberties, And ſhall further vpon the ſaid Certificate, procure a Licence vnder the hands of any foure of his Maieſties Priuie Councell, whereof the Lord Chancellour, Lord Treaſourer, Lord priuie Scale, and Chancellour of the Exchequer for the time being, to be two in allowance of the ſame, That in ſuch caſe ſuch perſon ſo building, ſhall not be deemed and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for an offender againſt his Maieſties Proclamations, any thing in the ſaid Proclamations, or either of them to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary hereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at our Mannour of Tuddington <date>the 25. day of Iuly in the ſixt yeere of our Raigne of Great Britaine, France and Ireland.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by the Deputies of Robert Barker, <hi>Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie. Anno</hi> 1608.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
